https://www.hiresafe.com/client-support/policies-and-procedures/privacy-policy/

Skip to content(888) 252-5561 | research@hiresafe.comClient LoginNewsletterEmployment Background Check Blog
Data Research Network Privacy Policy StatementData Research Network, Inc. dba: HireSafe, (“HireSafe”) is a Consumer Reporting Agency (CRA) that prepares Consumer Reports for its authorized End-User employer clients under the provisions of the federal Fair Credit Reporting Act (FCRA), state law equivalents, and international laws and regulations where applicable.HireSafe has created these statements and guidelines in order to demonstrate our firm commitment to privacy and we are committed to maintaining the highest degree of respect for the sensitive nature of the information obtained and under our control. HireSafe provides access only to legitimate businesses and licensed professionals who can demonstrate an appropriate need for and permissible use of the information.All information contained in the HireSafe. database is obtained either directly from government agencies, from third party businesses who have obtained public record, or publicly available information from its sources, or from credit bureaus. Information is obtained from various governmental agencies that provide information related to driver’s licenses, motor vehicles, real property records, death records and criminal histories.For purposes of this Notice:“Personal Data” means any information concerning an identified or identifiable individual; and“Consumer” means an individual; and“Consumer Report” means any written, oral, or other communication of any information by a consumer reporting agency bearing on a consumer's creditworthiness, credit standing, credit capacity, character, general reputation, personal characteristics, or mode of living which is used or expected to be used or collected in whole or in part for the purpose of serving as a factor in establishing the consumer's eligibility for employment; and“End-User” means the client entity that requests and obtains a background check report from HireSafe; and“Processing” means any operation with respect to Personal Data, such as collection, retrieval, access, use, disclosure, storage or disposal of Personal Data.HireSafe only collects Personal Data pursuant to written disclosure and authorization under the FCRA and other applicable domestic and international laws, and only disseminates consumer reports to End-Users as directed in the written authorization. Personal Data is only collected and distributed at your direction and with your written authorization. Your Personal Data is never shared with unauthorized third parties, it is never reused, and it is never resold.As part of their selection process, our End-User clients engage HireSafe to process background checks on both U.S. and Non-U.S. residents who apply for open positions located where they reside or for placement elsewhere. This Notice provides the following information about the background check process:What Personal Data End-Users may collect about you;How the End-User uses your Personal Data;To whom the End-User discloses your Personal Data;Any international transfers of your Personal Data;How the End-User and HireSafe safeguard your Personal Data;Whether End-Users engage in automated decision-making; andYour rights regarding your Personal Data.Our Collection, Use, and Disclosure of Your Personal DataCOLLECTION: The background check will involve verifying Personal Data that you have provided during the application process and the collection of additional information about you. Each End-User applies their own background check criteria, and HireSafe only processes the services we are instructed to perform by the End-User. Depending on the scope of inquiries requested by the End-User the background check may in whole or in part include, obtain, and/or verify: information about your prior employment; personal interviews with your former employers concerning your job performance and compensation; professional and personal references; education history; professional licenses and credentials; national insurance number, social security number or similar number, as applicable; and motor vehicle records. Where it is relevant to the position that you are seeking and to the extent permitted by applicable law, the background check may also collect information about your criminal convictions and offenses, if any; your credit history; and listings on debarment, sanctions, and exclusion lists, if any. Where legally permitted or required below, the background check may include drug and/or occupational health screening.USE: The information collected will be compiled in a Consumer Report (“Background Report”) that will contain your Personal Data. The requesting End-User will use the Background Report to evaluate your application for the open position. This evaluation is necessary for the requesting End-User to determine whether to enter into an employment or contracted work agreement with you and for the requesting End-User to pursue its legitimate interests of ensuring the fidelity of its workforce. If you do not provide the Personal Data necessary for the requesting End-User to conduct the background check, they may determine that you are not eligible for the position for which you applied.DISCLOSURE: The requesting End-User will not disclose the Background Report to any third party outside its corporate group except in exceptional circumstances, such as to seek advice from its professional advisors or to defend legal claims. If you apply for employment with another member of the End-User’s corporate group, the End-User may disclose the Background Report to that entity.Our Personal Information Disclosure: United States or OverseasINTERNATIONAL TRANSFERS OF PERSONAL DATAAll HireSafe facilities and employees are located in the United States which is where all Background Reports are prepared. HireSafe does not transmit, share, or transfer Personal Data outside the United States or its territories except in cases where a requested Background Report includes an international background check service and the Personal Data needed for performing the service is located outside of the U.S., and then HireSafe only transfers the minimum information needed to prepare the Background Report. All personal information is transmitted and stored in a secure manner in accordance with the terms of this Privacy Policy.HireSafe is compliant with the EU General Data Protection Regulation (“GDPR”) regarding the use and transfer of information on residents of the European Union.If you apply for a position with other members of the End-User’s corporate group, the Personal Data in the Background Report may be accessed by employees of those entities directly involved in the hiring process. These other entities may be located in third countries that provide different data protection standards from those in your country. You have the right to object to such transfers of your Personal Data to affiliated companies unless the recipient has entered into an appropriate data transfer agreement with the End-User.Our Security Measures for Personal DataWhether in possession of the End-User or HireSafe, your Personal Data will be protected by reasonable and appropriate administrative, physical, and technical measures. For example, HireSafe requires a unique username and password to access Background Reports, and the End-User provides such log-in credentials only to employees with a need to know; all personal data located in HireSafe’s database is fully encrypted in transit and at rest. The Privacy and Integrity of all Personal Data are fully protected. All employees who have access to any Personal Data have undergone initial and ongoing background checks, signed privacy agreements, and they are regularly trained in privacy practices and procedures. In the event of a data breach, HireSafe acts in conformity with appropriate domestic and international data breach laws.Our Retention of Personal DataPersonal Data is retained by HireSafe on U.S. residents for three (3) years unless otherwise restricted by national and/or international laws and regulations. Non-U.S. residents Personal Data is retained as allowed by the GDPR and/or other international laws and regulations.The primary method for a consumer to opt-out of HireSafe obtaining your Personal Data is to not consent to HireSafe preparing a Background Check for one of its End-User clients. Consent may be subsequently withdrawn by you after which HireSafe will stop processing and/or reporting your Personal Data. To withdraw consent, you may contact HireSafe by email at research@hiresafe.com or by calling  (888) 252-5561 and asking to speak with the Privacy Specialist.In the event, that HireSafe by either policy or request destroys any information provided by clients, applicants, or third parties during the course of its work the destruction is accomplished in accordance with the approved document disposal rules formulated by the Federal Trade Commission (FTC).The End-User will retain the Background Report until the conclusion of the job application process, and if you are not hired, for one additional year unless applicable law or internal policy requires a longer or shorter retention period. If you are hired, the End-User will retain the Background Report throughout the course of the employment relationship and for one additional year unless applicable law requires a longer or shorter retention period.Your Rights with Respect to Your Personal DataRight to Inspect: Any Consumer may exercise their right to inspect any data held about them and to object to any data pursuant to the FCRA, state law equivalents, and international laws and regulations where applicable. See "A Summary of Your Rights Under the Fair Credit Reporting Act" prepared by the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau (CFPB). Also, learn about your right to request a copy of your data on the FACT Act Compliance page. Residents of the EU will find the rights of the data subject under the GDPR by clicking here.Right to Correction: You have the right to access your Personal Data and to request that the requesting End-User and HireSafe update, correct or delete your Personal Data as provided by applicable U.S. and international laws.Right to Object: You also have the right to restrict, and to object to, the requesting End-User’s processing of your Personal Data and to data portability as provided by applicable law. Subject to certain limitations, the right to data portability allows you to obtain from the requesting End-User, or to ask them to send to a third party in electronic form, a copy of your Personal Data that you provided to the requesting End-User in connection with the background check process or as otherwise obtained with your other consent.Right to Access: Your right to access your Personal Data includes your right to receive a copy of all, or a portion, of your Personal Data in the End-User’s or HireSafe’s possession as long as their providing your Personal Data would not adversely affect the rights and freedoms of others.Right to Dispute: If you are the subject of a consumer report prepared by HireSafe and find incorrect or incomplete information, you have the right under federal and international laws to dispute it. Consumers may contact HireSafe by calling (888) 252-5561 and asking to speak with the Consumer Relations Specialist, or by sending an email with your contact information to research@hiresafe.com. For more information, visit the HireSafe Consumer Support Center.GDPR Right To Object: You have the right to restrict, and object to the processing of your Personal Data and to data portability as provided by applicable law. If you do object to the processing of your Personal Data, the processing of your Personal Data will be stopped unless there is an overriding, compelling reason to continue the processing or the processing is necessary to establish, pursue or defend legal claims. Subject to certain limitations, the right to data portability allows you to obtain from the requesting End-User, or to ask them to send to a third party, a copy of your Personal Data in electronic form that you provided to the requesting End-User in connection with the background check process or with your consent.GDPR Right to Erasure: You have the right to have your Personal Data erased if:The Personal Data is no longer necessary for the purpose for which it was originally collected or processed it for;You withdraw your consent;You object to the processing of your data, and there is no overriding legitimate interest to continue this processing; andYour Personal Data was processed unlawfully (i.e., in breach of the lawfulness requirement of the 1st principle of the GDPR).How to Exercise Your GDPR Rights: You can exercise these rights by contacting the requesting End-User for further information and assistance. The requesting End-User will respond to such requests in accordance with applicable data protection law. If you reside in the European Economic Area, you have the right to lodge a complaint with the applicable data protection authority if you believe that your Personal Data has been processed in violation of applicable data protection law. You may also contact HireSafe directly by email at research@hiresafe.com or by calling (888) 252-5561 and asking to speak with the Privacy Specialist. Contact HireSafe for Privacy Questions or ConcernsAny questions or concerns about Privacy should be directed to research@hiresafe.com. HireSafe will make all reasonable efforts to address a consumer's concerns. If the matter cannot be resolved by HireSafe, then a consumer has additional rights. See "A Summary of Your Rights Under the Fair Credit Reporting Act". Residents of the EU will find the rights of the data subject under the GDPR by clicking here.Right to ModifyHireSafe reserves the right to modify or change its privacy policy. All such changes will be posted on this page. Last revision: 03/10/2020Questions?If you have questions regarding the HireSafe Privacy Policy, please contact:Alfred Firato
President and CEO
Data Research Network, Inc. dba: HireSafe
2228 Longport Court, Suite 130
Elk Grove, CA  95758 USA
Telephone: (916) 226-2550 | (888) 252-5561
Email: aafirato@hiresafe.comReady to find out more?Request a FREE background check service consultation!
Click Here
Quick Callback
Request More Information Talk with a Screening Specialist!Enter your information below and a screening specialist will call you as soon as possible.Phone*Name*Best time to call*Our office is open week days 9-5 Pacific Time. Call backs requested ASAP are usually made within one hour of form submission during those hours.Time Zone*How did you hear about us?
Google
Bing
Yahoo
Facebook
Twitter
LinkedIn
Referral
OtherPhoneThis field is for validation purposes and should be left unchanged.
Screening SolutionsBackground Check OptionsEnvision Suite – Most Popular PackagesEchelon Suite – Higher ResponsibilityEncompass Specialty Suite – Position SpecificEnterprise HirePlazaDOT & Transportation Background ChecksNERC-CIP Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety AdministrationEmployment Drug TestingDOT Drug TestingEmployee Drug TestingDrug Testing SupportSupervisor Awareness TrainingApplicant Tracking System – ATSSolutions by IndustrySolutions by ServiceComplianceAdverse ActionFCRA LawsuitsFair Credit Reporting Act Background Check ComplianceForm I-9 E-Verify & Employment EligibilityState ComplianceHow a HireSafe Background Check worksWhy HireSafe?Data SecurityWho we are and what we doHireSafe HistoryFamily Legacy of ServiceClient SupportBackground Check InformationHow Does a Background Check Work?Background check processing formatsGlossaryMulti-State Criminal Database InformationHow to use the HireSafe portalContact UsDispute a HireSafe background check reportFAQ’sPolicies and ProceduresData SecurityPrivacy PolicyRed Flag PolicySurcharges & Imposed FeesTerms and Conditions of UseVerification ProceduresResource LibrarySign-Up
